<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
			 "/home/arl/lib/docbk/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY release "memphis">
<!ENTITY Release "Memphis">
]>

<article lang="en">

<articleinfo>
   <title>Quickstart Guide: FMS atmospheric dynamical cores</title>

   <abstract>
      <para>
This document describes how to acquire, compile, and run specific test cases of
four solo FMS atmospheric dynamical core models. The available codes are a
finite-difference B-grid model, a spectral transform model, and a "vertically
Lagrangian" finite-volume model running the Held-Suarez GCM benchmark.  Also
included are a B-grid shallow water model and two simple spectral variations, a
spectral barotropic model and spectral shallow water model.
      </para>
      <para>
For more information, see the <ulink url="guide.html">User's Guide</ulink>
which is included in this package and also accessible from the <ulink
url="http://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/~fms">FMS Homepage</ulink>.  
      </para>
   </abstract>

   <author>
      <firstname>Amy</firstname>
      <surname>Langenhorst</surname>
      <email>Amy.Langenhorst@noaa.gov</email>
   </author>
</articleinfo>


<section id="acquire">
   <title>Acquire the Source Code</title>
   <para>
The Flexible Modeling System development team at GFDL uses a local implementation of GForge to
serve FMS software, located at <ulink url="http://fms.gfdl.noaa.gov"/>.
In order to obtain the source code, you must 
<ulink url="https://fms.gfdl.noaa.gov/account/register.php">register</ulink>
as an FMS user on our software server.  
After submitting the registration form on the software server, you should
receive an automatically generated confirmation email within a few minutes.  
Clicking on the link in the email confirms the creation of your account.
   </para>
   <para>
After your account has been created, you should 
<ulink url="https://fms.gfdl.noaa.gov/account/login.php">log in</ulink> 
and request access to the FMS Atmospheric Dynamical Cores project.
Once the FMS project administrator grants you access, you will
receive a second e-mail notification.  This email requires action on the part of the project administrator
and thus may take longer to arrive.  The email will contain instructions for
obtaining the release package, which are described below.  
   </para>
   <para>
The download will create a directory called <filename>atm_dycores</filename> in
your current working directory containing the release package. The
<ulink url="../readme">readme</ulink> file in the
<filename>atm_dycores</filename> directory gives a brief overview of the
package's directory structure and contents.
   </para> 
   <para>
Sample output is also available for download.  See <xref linkend="examine"/> for
more information on the sample output.
   </para>
</section>

<section id="run">
   <title>Run the Model</title>

<section id="provided">
   <title>The Provided Sample Experiments</title>

   <para>
This release includes six sample experiments in the directory <ulink url="../exp/"><filename>atm_dycores/exp</filename></ulink>.
Each runs one of the atmospheric dynamical core models, which are:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>B-grid</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A hydrostatic, finite difference primative equation GCM.
 A complete description can be found at <ulink url="../src/atmos_bgrid/documentation/bgrid.pdf"/>.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>B-grid Shallow Water</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A B-grid model of shallow incompressible fluid dynamics.
 A description of the B-grid dynamical core can be found at <ulink url="../src/atmos_bgrid/documentation/bgrid.pdf"/>.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>Spectral</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A hydrostatic, spectral primative equation GCM.
 A complete description can be found at <ulink url="../src/atmos_spectral/documentation/spectral_core.pdf"/>.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>Spectral Shallow Water</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A spectral model of shallow incompressible fluid dynamics.
 A complete description can be found at <ulink url="../src/atmos_spectral_shallow/shallow.pdf"/>.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>Spectral Barotropic</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A spectral model of non-divergent incompressible fluid dynamics.
 A complete description can be found at <ulink url="../src/atmos_spectral_barotropic/barotropic.pdf"/>.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis>Finite Volume</emphasis></para>
         <para>
 A "vertically Lagrangian" finite-volume model.
 A complete description can be found in 
         </para>
         <para>
Lin, S-J., 2004: <emphasis role="bold">A "vertically Lagrangian" finite-volume dynamical core for global models.</emphasis>
<emphasis>Monthly Weather Review</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">132(10)</emphasis>, 2293-2307.
         </para>
         <para>
<ulink url="http://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/reference/bibliography/2004/sjl0402.html">Abstract</ulink>  /
<ulink url="http://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/reference/bibliography/2004/sjl0402.pdf">PDF</ulink>
         </para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="description">
   <title>Functionality of the Sample Runscripts</title>
      <para>
The runscripts provided in each <ulink url="../exp"><filename>exp/$dycore</filename></ulink> directory
perform the minimum required steps to run the models and are intended only 
as a starting point for the development of more practical runscripts. 
The sample script:
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>
compiles the <command>mppnccombine</command> executable for multiprocessing platforms,
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
compiles and links the model source code,
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
creates a working directory where the model will be run,
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
creates or copies the required input data into the working directory, and
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
runs the model.
         </para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
Note that the directory paths and file paths are variables. They are initially set to correspond 
to the directory structure as it exists upon download, but are made variables to 
accommodate changes to this directory structure.
      </para>
      <para> 
The diagnostic fields output from the models is mulithreaded. That
is, each processor writes a separate file which includes data only from its own
portion of the globe (its "domain"). A utility named <command>mppnccombine</command> is supplied
which is executed after the model execution is complete and which combines
these into a single file which covers the entire globe. For a complete
description of <command>mppnccombine</command> see the 
<ulink url="guide.html#mppnccombine">mppnccombine documentation</ulink>
in the user's guide.  
      </para>
      <para>
The output is not moved from the working directory, archiving of output is left to the user.
The files needed to restart the model are left in the working directory's subdirectory called 
<filename>RESTART</filename>. If it is desired to restart the model from this state, do the following:
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
Move the files in <filename>$workdir/RESTART</filename> to
<filename>$workdir/INPUT</filename>.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
The <command>mppnccombine</command> utility will not overwrite preexisting diagnostic field files
in <filename>$workdir</filename>, so they must be moved or renamed before restarting.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
Comment the <command>if ( -e $workdir )</command> block in the runscript, which prevents
accidental reuse of the working directory.
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
You can then execute the runscript again.
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>
</section>

<section id="portability">
   <title>Portability Issues with the Sample Runscripts</title>
      <para>
If you encounter a compile error when executing the sample runscript, please first check whether 
you have correctly customized your <command>mkmf</command> template. 
The scripts use the <command>mkmf</command> utility, which creates make files to facilitate 
compilation. 
The <command>mkmf</command> utility uses a platform-specific template for setting up system and platform
dependent parameters.  Sample templates for various platforms are provided in the 
<ulink url="../bin"><filename>atm_dycores/bin</filename></ulink> directory.  You may need to consult your system administrator
to set up a compilation template for your
platform and ensure the locations for system libraries are defined correctly.  
For a complete description of <command>mkmf</command> see the 
<ulink url="../bin/mkmf.html">mkmf documentation</ulink>.

The <userinput>$platform</userinput> variable in the runscript is used to separate 
and identify platform-specific items in the runscript, including the <command>mkmf</command> template.
      </para>
      <para>
The execution is accomplished with a utility called <command>mpirun</command>, which is unique to machines by 
Silicon Graphics. This may need to be changed to run on other platforms.
      </para>
</section>

<section id="changing">
   <title>Changing the Sample Runscripts</title>
   
   <section id="length">
      <title>Changing the length of the run and atmospheric time step</title>
      <para>
By default the scripts are set up to run only one or two days.  The run length is controlled by the
namelist <literal>main_nml</literal> which is set directly in the runscripts for convenience.  
To increase the run length to 200 days, change the namelist parameter <literal>days</literal>
in the runscript as follows.  The other parameter in the namelist, <literal>dt_atmos</literal>, 
controls the atmospheric time step.  
<programlisting>
 &amp;main_nml
     days   = 200,
     dt_atmos = 1800 /
</programlisting>
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="npes">
      <title>Changing the number of processors</title>
      <para>
By default the scripts are set up to run with the MPI library, but only on one processor.
To increase the number of processors, change the <userinput>$npes</userinput> variable
at the top of the sample runscript.  You may need to consult the documentation for each
particular model concerning appropriate processor counts for that model.
      </para>
      <para>
To run without the MPI library, do the following:
   <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
Make sure you are only using one processor, ie, the variable <userinput>$npes</userinput>
is set to 1 at the top of the sample runscript.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
Change the run command in the runscript from 
"<userinput>mpirun -np $npes fms.x</userinput>" to simply
"<userinput>fms.x</userinput>".
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
Remove the <userinput>-Duse_libMPI</userinput> from the <userinput>mkmf</userinput> line
in the runscript.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
Remove the <userinput>-lmpi</userinput> from the <userinput>$LIBS</userinput> variable
in your mkmf template. 
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
Move or remove your previous compilation directory (specified as <userinput>$execdir</userinput> 
in the runscript) so that all code must be recompiled.
      </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
      </para>
   </section> 


</section>
</section>

<section id="examine">
<title>Examine the Output</title>
   <para>
     You may download sample output data for comparison at
     <ulink url="https://fms.gfdl.noaa.gov/projects/fms/">https://fms.gfdl.noaa.gov/projects/fms/</ulink>
     under the "Files" tab. 
     Each tar file expands to a directory containing a
     readme file along with netcdf and ascii output. The files
     <filename>bgrid_output.tar.gz</filename>,
     <filename>fv_output.tar.gz</filename> and
     <filename>spectral_output.tar.gz</filename> contain daily snapshots of
     surface pressure and time means of all fields over the 200 to 1200 day
     period. The file <filename>bgrid_shallow_output.tar.gz</filename> contains
     daily snapshots of surface pressure and time means of all fields over a
     30 day period. The file
     <filename>spectral_barotropic_output.tar.gz</filename> contains 1000 days
     of diagnostic output with a 200 day spin-up period for the spectral
     barotropic model. <filename>spectral_shallow_output.tar.gz</filename>
     contains 30 days of diagnostic output for the spectral shallow water
     model.
   </para>

</section>


</article>
